Guide to the Ralph G. Allen Burlesque Collection, 1905-1962 CTC.1972.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Ralph G. Allen Burlesque Collection
1905-1962
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Allen, Ralph G.
CTC.1972.02
1.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
This collection contains approx. 150 scripts of burlesque sketches and 9 audio recordings of interviews and performances compiled by Ralph G. Allen and his colleague John Ulrich in a 1962 project funded by the Charles E. Merrill Faculty Fellowship at the University of Pittsburgh. Materials were drawn from the personal recollections and records of Jess Mack, Billy "Cheese and Crackers" Hagan ("baggy pants" comedian), Billy Foster, Irving Harman, and Jack Coyle.
Biography
Ralph G. Allen (1934-2004), was born in Philadelphia and graduated summa cum laude from Amherst College in 1955. In 1960 he received the Doctor of Fine Arts degree from Yale University School of Drama where he held the MCA Fellowship in Playwriting and was a John Golden Fellow. In 1965 he was awarded a Guggenheim Fellowship. His alma mater, Amherst College, awarded him a Doctor of Humane Letters degree in 1980.
A former University of Pittsburgh faculty member, Allen was a writer, director, teacher, historian, and theatrical advisor who served the John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, UCLA, the University of Victoria, New York University School of the Arts, The University of Tennessee, and Queens College.
While in residence at the University of Pittsburgh, Allen collaborated with Professor John Ulrich with the aid of a Charles E. Merrill Faculty Fellowship, to compile Burlesque sketches from comedian Billy Hagan's personal collection and interviews from performers Billy Foster, Bert Carr, Maxie Furman, Irving Harman, Jack Coyle, and Billy "Cheese and Crackers" Hagan.
Allen co-conceived the Tony awarding winning musical, Sugar Babies, and frequently published scholarly articles on the burlesque. His play, A Horse of a Different Color, premiered at the Three Rivers Shakespeare Festival in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania.
Scope and Content Notes
Series I contains a collection of burlesque skits compiled from the personal records of Jess Mack of Boston, an agent and former Burlesque Performer. Series II contains audio recordings of burlesque performances of Billy Hagan, Frank X. Silk, Lou Browne, Floyd Hallicy and interviews with Billy Hagan, Billy Foster, Irving Harman, and Jack Coyle.
Arrangement
Series I. Burlesque skits
Series II. Audio reels
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ralph G. Allen in 1972.
Previous Citation
Ralph G. Allen Burlesque Collection, ca. 1905-1962, CTC.1972.02, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Ralph G. Allen Burlesque Collection, ca. 1905-1962, CTC.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Boston (Mass.); Theater; Theater -- United States; Actors; Audiotapes; Performing arts -- United States; Vaudeville; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Burlesques; University of Pittsburgh; Allen, Ralph G.; Coyle, Jack; Foster, Billy; Hagan, Billy; Hallicy, Floyd; Harman, Irving; Mack, Jess; Silk, Frank X.; Ulrich, John
- Burlesque Skits, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I contains a collection of burlesque skits compiled from the personal records of Jess Mack of Boston, an agent and former Burlesque Performer. Some of the skits have multiple copies or different versions within the same folder.
  - Egg in the hat (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - In Mexico (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Oriental bit in one watch and money (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Quaker girl (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The race (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Radio bit (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Radio material (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Radio scene (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Rag time duel (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ragged coat bit (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The raid (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Recitation (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Red and green traffic light scene (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Red rose bit (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Reform (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Renting a room (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Renting half an office (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Restaurant scene (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - The returned soldier (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Room 202 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - The rose (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Rubber plant (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Rubber scene (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Russian Bolshevik scene (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - S.A. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Safety deposit vault (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Sailor scene (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Sailors return (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Salesman (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Sally don't live in our alley no more and Why don't you marry (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Saloon scene (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Sarah the snake (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Saratoga Springs (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - School days (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Scotch blood blackout (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Scrutinizing scene (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Selling a theatre (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Selling clothes (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - 72nd Street (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Sherlock Holmes detective agency (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - The sheik (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Shimmy scene (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Shirt back to back bit (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Shoe store (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Silverware (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Six feet in bed (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - A slight mistake (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Slogan wise (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Smith baby scene (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - So young and innocent scene (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - A social inconvenience (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Soft and loud scene (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Soldier Bill (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Song and dance troupe (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Spanish bullfight (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Spanish version (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Speech kissing bit (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Spot bit (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Stage door bit in one (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Stage door scene (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Stand in scene (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Standing on my feet (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - States recitations (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Static bit (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Street cleaner cart (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Street cleaning bit (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Street walker (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Subway scene (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Suffragette (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Suicide scene (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Swat the fly (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Sweet singer (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Syncopated entrance for two comics (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - System kiss bit (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Table scene (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Tailor bootlegger bit (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Take em to the door blues (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Take off my pants (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Take out the deuces and trays (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Talkative salesman (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Teasie weasie (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Telegram scene (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Telephone bit (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Telephone booth (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - That's my wife (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Theatre bit (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Theatre box office (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Third degree (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 3 A.M. or taking a sweetheart home (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Three detectives (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Three drunks (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Three people act (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Three suitcase scene (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Three waiters (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Title bit (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Tongue and cheese sandwich scene (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Tony the spider (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Topics bit (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Tough bit (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Traffic cop (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Train hold up (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Train scene (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - The traveling salesman (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Travesty scene (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Trim scene (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Trying to get arrested (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Two cop scene (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Two gilters from Boston (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Two of the four hundred (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Under the table (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Upside down business (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Upstairs (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Vacuum cleaner scene (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - The vagabond lovers (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Valencia (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - The vampire (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Vanishing scene (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Vaudeville hokem dance art (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Waiter strike bit (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - War debt (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Wardrobe or kitchen scene (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Westfall murder case (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Where is Nellie? (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Whiskey in club bit (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Whiskey taster bit (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - White seal (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Whiz & wham (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Who died first (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - The widow and the bachelor (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Widow scene (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Wild cat wild (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Winter scene - old jaw bone (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Wise child court (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Wise guy (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Wishing book (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Within the law (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - The woman I've been going with for the past three years (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Woman scene (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - The woman who pays (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Women court room scene (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - The wrestlers (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Wrinkles scene (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - The wrong flat (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Yes sir, that's my baby (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - You ain't got it (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - You got to have it in Hollywood (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - You hit the spot; stormy weather (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - You're standing on my feet (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - You're a liar bit (Box 2, Folder 75)
- Audio Tapes, II.; 9 reel-to-reel
  Series II contains audio recordings of burlesque performances of Billy Hagan, Frank X. Silk, Lou Browne, Floyd Hallicy and interviews with Billy Hagan, Billy Foster, Irving Harman, and Jack Coyle.
  - Interview with Billy Hagan, May 8, 1962 (Box 3, Reel 1-2)
  - Interviews with Billy Hagan, Billy Foster, Irving Harman, and Jack Coyle Wheel #1, May 7, 1962 (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - Interviews with Billy Hagan, Jack Coyle, Irving Harman, and Billy Foster, April 11, 1962 (Box 3, Reel 4)
  - Interviews with Billy Hagan, Ralph and Harriet Allen, Irving Harman, and Larry V Heller, May 9, 1962 (Box 3, Reel 5)
  - Interviews with Irving Harman, Billy Hagan, Billy Foster, and Jack Coyle, May 9, 1962 (Box 3, Reel 6)
  - Interviews with Billy Hagan, Billy Foster, and Joe Bock, May 10, 1962 (Box 3, Reel 7)
  - Burlesque show at Lyric Theatre in Allentown, PA, Jan 16, 1960 (Box 3, Reel 8)
  - Interviews with Irving Harman, Billy Hagan, Billy Foster, and Jack Coyle (Reel 2), May 11, 1962 (Box 3, Reel 9)